# KIM SUNDEEN

## Full Stack Software Engineer | Mapper | GISP | Project Coordinator

%https://ksundeen.github.io ⊠kim.h.sundeen@gmail.com 📞 218.590.1330 💡 Duluth, MN

**LIFE PHILOPHY** "The only mistake is one from which you didn't learn" -A Friend



### **SUMMARY**

Kim is an energetic & quick learner as full stack software engineer in the GIS landscape. With 12 years of experience architecting, developing, & implementing progressive full stack GIS application solutions, she always focuses on improving the end-user's experience, back-end design & solution maintenance. Kim is an expert in GIS database management, desktop, & mobile application development. She keeps her skills current by leading workshops, completing online training, & coordinating user groups.

## **LANGUAGES & TECHNOLOGIES**

- **Web development**: Typescript, HTML5, CSS, JavaScript frameworks, node.js, npm/yarn, Angular, React
- Code Versioning: Git, Github, Mercurial, TortoiseSVN, TFS
- **OS**: Windows, Linux, Mac
- Server-side/desktop programming: Python, C# .NET, SQL/PLSQL, ASP.NET MVC, GeoServer web publishing
- Database design/structures: Microsoft SQL Server, 11g/12c Oracle, PostgreSQL, MySQL, MS Access, Excel
- ArcGIS Enterprise stack: ArcGIS Server, Web Adapter, ArcSDE, Portal, Data store, ArcGIS Online
- Mapping APIs: Esri's JavaScript API 3.x, 4.x, Leaflet, Mapbox, Google Maps, Openlayers 5/6, Boundless SDK (React-based OpenLayers)
- GIS/GPS/Mobile Apps: ArcGIS 9.x-10.x, ArcGIS Pro 2.x, QGIS 2-3, Google Earth KML, Garmin, ArcPad, Terrasync, & Pathfinder Office, Survey 123, ArcGIS for Collector, Web AppBuilder Developer Edition, ArcGIS Online

#### **SOFT SKILLS**

- Staff Supervision: Managed remote development teams for software development, performing code reviews collaboratively, & database configuration using agile project management with <u>GCR, Inc.</u> & <u>RAMTeCH</u>. Oversaw & trained student GIS technicians on GIS data entry procedures for <u>UW Nursing School</u> mapping projects & LTE staff for short-term land ownership projects with the <u>Bad River Tribe</u>.
- Agile Scrum Coaching: Coordinate team of 10 spatial and non-spatial developers as scrum master role to improve team collaboration & improve development efficiency for <u>GCR, Inc</u>. Lead two teams as scrum master for 10-member client software development team & internal projects for <u>MN Power</u> (3-person team).
- Workshop Presentations & Training: Taught introductory Python, JavaScript, GPS & GIS sessions for small group workshops on:

   (1) using new mapping & GPS programs
   (2) ArcGIS Desktop & opensource QGIS,
   (3) process for updating website front ends, &
   (4) GIS user needs & feasibility assessments,
   (5) Lead yearly workshops Esri's Utility Network Tools, Opensource GIS, & Jupyter Python notebooks (see full details: <a href="https://ksundeen.github.io/portfolio.html#media">https://ksundeen.github.io/portfolio.html#media</a>
- Presentations & Graphic Design: See my web-portfolio for examples: <a href="https://ksundeen.github.io/gallery.html">https://ksundeen.github.io/gallery.html</a>; Awarded 1st Place: Large-format map, 2014 National Tribal GIS Conference, "A Bird's Eye View of the Bad River Watershed & Proposed Mine."
- Technical & Scientific Writing: Wrote & awarded \$3,000 free Azure credits grant for MN GIS/LIS non-profit. \$127,000 FEMA grant, \$10,000 University of Wisconsin-Madison research grant, & \$5,200 ESRI Conservation Grant Program grant. Published perreviewed research articles on GIS, modeling, & wildlife research.

#### **EDUCATION & CERTIFICATIONS**

- Continued Education: software engineering through UW-Madison, Lake Superior College, PluralSight, LinkedIn Learning
- 2017 2018 Graduate Courses in University of Wisconsin-Madison, Master of Science (GIS Web Map Programming)
  - Biking Route Finder (Google Maps API & Postgresql database to highlight optimal biking routes around Duluth based on the user's preference for terrain, slope, social media tweets, & proximity to bikes -<a href="https://ksundeen.github.io/assets/videos/CycleRoutesIntro">https://ksundeen.github.io/assets/videos/CycleRoutesIntro</a> small.mp4
- 2012 Certified Geographic Information Systems Professional (GISP) #84940
- 2012 University of Wisconsin-Madison, Graduate Certificate: Geographic Information Systems
  - o **Focus:** geostatistical regression of remotely-sensed mercury concentrations & data science methods.
- 2011 University of Wisconsin-Madison, Master of Science: Conservation Biology & Sustainable Development
  - o **Focus:** predictive spatial models to detect wildlife & electric distribution power line risks.
- 2006 University of Wisconsin-Madison, Bachelor of Science: Wildlife Ecology, Certificate: Environmental Studies

Kim H. Sundeen Page 1 of 4

#### PROJECT EXPERIENCE

- Web Map App Development & Implementation: Planned & developed custom opensource OpenLayers & ArcGIS web mapping applications & designed & trained on configuring Google Analytics web tracking for improving web marketing for:
  - o GCR, Inc.: Boundless SDK, Open Layers web viewer built within MVC .NET framework.
  - Lake Superior Consulting: Engineering web viewers in Angular & C# frameworks using Esri's API 3.x,
  - Bad River Tribe: Ownership & Lease Viewer (ArcGIS Flex Viewer & SDE database),
  - o City of Duluth: Street Update Viewer (Esri's Web App Builder & SDE database),
  - o MN Power: Electric Utility Asset Identification (Esris' JavaScript API & Web AppBuilder Developer's Edition & SDE database),
  - o Biking Route Finder (Google Maps API & Postgresql database).
- **Best Practice Code Standardization & Unit Testing:** Researched & implemented best practices for UI design, unit testing for React, JavaScript, Python, & React.js code design for *GCR, Inc*.
- ArcGIS Service Publishing Automation: Developed configuration-driven python solution for other clients to quickly publish 20-40 GIS web services between different development/staging/production environments through ArcMap into ArcGIS Server 10.6. This process saved 3-4 hours/day of manual error-prone service publishing. Created ArcGIS add-ins & published REST geoprocessing tools into ArcGIS Server to simplify <u>City of Duluth's</u> street & pavement updates for users.
- GIS Data Migration for Gas UPDM New Utility Network: Lead agile software development & project planning for client & consultant teams for <u>RAMTeCH</u> to customize python-plsql oracle database migration solutions to handle ETL from 5 source databases to one unified model. Managed multiple Esri alpha/beta software releases for changes in the new Utility Network model.
- **GIS Workflow & Process Improvement:** Coordinated GIS feasibility study to understand how users interact & use the applications. The results are used to develop clear tool requirements for <u>Lake Superior Consulting</u> app tool development. Documented workflows for engineering staff at *City of Duluth* to identify areas for improvement. Learned established GIS data entry policies.
- Full Cycle Project Development & Implementation: Implemented new software release & testing standards with GCR, Inc. including: 1) software development & unit testing, 2) software code review & testing), 3) code documentation & architecture design. Coordinated GIS user needs assessment & implementation plans for 19 projects for software development, database development & improvements, training, & website enhancements for City of Duluth IT Dept. & Public Works & Utilities Dept. Priorities were used to direct funding to most important projects. Conducted GIS feasibility & UX/UI study for Lake Superior Consulting that clearly identified user, business, & technical requirements for 10 new development tools.
- **GIS Data Security:** Implemented new ArcGIS Server security protocol for publishing GIS services online; Researched & re-wrote external & internal data-sharing agreements & policies for the *Bad River Tribe*.

#### **WORK EXPERIENCE**

5/2019 – GIS Developer

New Orleans, LA (remote in Duluth, MN)

present GCR, Inc – Software Development

**Summary:** Work as lead GIS Developer & Spatial Architect in an Agile software development team to design, engineer solutions, & deliver new opensource GIS tools, maps, & user interfaces using back-end & front-end development technologies in the Real Estate Department for public sector clients. Specializing in GeoServer, OpenLayers API to work with WMS/WFS OGC standards to reference various PostgreSQL, building upon Boundless/Planet Federal (an OpenLayers library) using React.js, node.js, & Redux state management libraries for GIS UI development inside an ASP.NET MVC application. Develop clear business requirements to provide software development tasks & priorities to other developers.

- GIS Business Strategy Lead strategy & technical requirements meetings with business analysts & software developers to clarify user & software requirements, which reduced software release to QA testing down from 3 weeks to 1 week.
- Team Leadership & Collaboration Onboarded developers with training sessions resulting in increased software
  releases & productivity. Facilitated independent learning environment leading to higher quality software output.
  Served as technical manager for team of three developers to prioritize work, & unblock their issues. Provided team guidance,
  support, training, and mentorship to facilitate professional development.
- GIS App & Tool Development Engineered modular map-centric applications using React.js framework (Boundless SDK),
  OpenLayers, PostgreSQL, & Geoserver, with integrations with SQL Server databases for parcel research & management.

Kim H. Sundeen Page 2 of 4

### 5/2018-5/2019 GIS Developer



#### Lake Superior Consulting - Software Development

- GIS Business Strategy Conducted GIS feasibility & UX/UI study that clearly identified user, business, & technical requirements
  for 10 new development tools. Lead clearly defined research efforts & client presentations on implementing &
  architecting new mobile mapping systems that delivered immediate use for client projects with aggressive deadlines.
- Team & Project Management Implemented new team and meeting planning to reduce meeting and improve productivity. Collaborated with clients & software engineers/IT professionals to improve knowledge transfer to increase & knowledge transfer within departments & gather better business requirements. My efforts reduced the time from idea to implemented solution from 2 months to 3 weeks.
- GIS App & Tool Development Engineered applications using Esri, SharePoint, Primavera, & SQL Server integrations used by over 200 users. Used web frameworks to align, extend, & develop existing tools & programs (Angular, TypeScript, jQuery), backend internal applications (ASP.NET MVVM, C#, .NET), & GIS tools (Python 2.7, 3.x, Esri's JavaScript API 3.x, 4.x).

# 2/2017-5/2018 GIS Analyst/Developer

Stillwater, MN (remote in Duluth, MN)

## RAMTeCH Software Solutions – Professional Services

- Redesigned Practices & Coached Clients in Agile Lead as Scum Master for 10-member team to re-architect client software development life cycle & direct funds for applications & tools. Lead general & detailed client-focused user-training/demos.
- Engineered Data Migration & ETL Software Tools for Clients Designed, built, tested, & released C#, Python & SQL gas & electric utility network migration toolsets accessing Oracle 11g/12g SDE databases, ArcMap & Pro desktop tools that seamlessly handled ETL from 5 source databases to one unified model for Esri's new Utility Network as 1st official Esri implementation.
- Developed & Presented AWS Workshops for Clients & Conferences Worked with MN GIS/LIS Consortium to use ArcGIS
   Enterprise software for gas, electric, water, & utility operators using virtual AWS production environments.

## 4/2016-2/2017 GIS Programmer Analyst



#### Minnesota Power – Facility Operations

- Mobile Mapping Application/Survey Tool Development Developed, implemented, & trained staff on GIS services & geoprocessing tools through ArcGIS Server/ArcGIS Online for mobile data entry & data-transfer. Created Python routines to download & extract ArcGIS Online data & images from a Survey123 app & export to PDF with hyperlinked images & a summary of data from multiple related tables within a database. Developed MN Power's Electric Utility Asset Identification using Esri's JavaScript API & Web AppBuilder Developer's Edition & SDE database.
- Software Training & Developing Documentation Standards Trained staff on Esri's Model Builder, Python, & ArcGIS Online for utility edits, work order, & field tools systems. Documented publishing workflows in Survey123, ArcGIS Collector, & web maps.

# 2/2015-4/2016 GIS Specialist



#### City of Duluth - Engineering Division

- GIS Web Map Software Project Management Designed & managed a GIS user needs assessment & implementation for 19
  projects for software development, database development/improvements, & training for City of Duluth IT Department, Public
  Works, & Utilities. Developed City of Duluth Street Update Viewer web application.
- User Training & Presentations Lead monthly knowledge transfer user groups & designed new user training for new systems.
- Multiuser Database Management & Data Editing Edited gas, water, & storm GIS data in versioned SQL Server SDE databases.
   Expanded existing GIS map services to Python-built geoprocessing services to automate web map updates.

# 9/2012-2/2015 GIS Specialist

Odanah, WI

#### Bad River Tribe - Natural Resources Department

- Survey Field Collection, Processing, & Training Managed diverse field data collection preparation, training, pre- & postprocessing for surveys on roads, historical properties, utilities, & tree inventories using Esri's ArcPad, in Trimble GeoXH series.
- Map Creation, Analysis, & Automation Designed & trained non-developers to use Python to manipulate, re-write, or edit
  raster/vector data for use in GIS analysis & remote sensing apps (image enhancements, transforms, & radiometric/atmospheric
  correction). Deployed Tribal Ownership & Lease Viewer (ArcGIS Flex Viewer & SDE database).
- Data Creation, Maintenance & Standardization for Natural Resources Website Designed GIS databases for all depts.,
   planned & published data-entry web maps, & updated tribal website. Added secured & public Google, Esri's JavaScript API,
   ArcGIS Online, & GeoMoose OpenLayers web maps. Implemented ArcGIS Server security protocol for REST services.

Kim H. Sundeen Page **3** of **4** 

#### **ACHIEVEMENTS**

#### **Notable Presentations & Workshops**

- 2019. "Building, Branding, & Boosting your Web Portfolio with Github Pages & Google Analytics." Women in Tech Duluth User's Group, Feb.
- Sundeen, K.H. (2018). "Exploring the Utility Network in ArcGIS Pro for Water, Electric, & Gas Networks." MN GIS/LIS Fall Workshop, Oct.
- 2018. Sharing Code, Maps, & Data Science Through a Digital Jupyter Notebook." Duluth.NET Meetup group, June.
- 2017 & 2018. "Exploring the Utility Network in ArcGIS Pro." MN GIS/LIS Spring & Fall Workshop.
- 2017. Early Adopters of the Gas Utility Network: Are You the Tortoise or the Hare? Esri's GeoConX Conference, Sept.
- 2016. "Simplifying Metadata Editing for the Non-Programmer." Northern MN GIS User Group, April.
- 2016. "Designing a Long-Term GIS Vision & Implementation Plan." MN GIS/LIS Pre-Conference Workshop, Oct.
- 2015. "From the Field through the Firewall: An Approach to Streamlining Utility GIS Data Access in the Field, Office, & Web." MN GIS/LIS Conference, Oct.
- 2015. "Bringing Free & Open Source GIS to India Country." WI Land Information Association, Feb.

#### **Organizations & Affiliations**

- Director (2018-2019): Launched & lead Duluth Women in Tech/Women Who Code groups to learn & present professionally.
- Co-coordinator (2018) .NET Duluth meetup groups for developers for presentations & professional development
- Conference Committee Member (2018-Present): Minnesota GIS/LIS Conference, Virtual Environment Task Force
- Conference Committee Member 2016-2017: Minnesota GIS/LIS Conference, Workshop Committee
- Board of Directors (2014-2015): Wisconsin Land Information Association (WLIA), Chair of Membership Committee
- Committee Member (2014-2015): National Tribal Geographic Information Support Center (NTGISC), Publications Committee

Kim H. Sundeen Page **4** of **4**